[Music]
at
Professor so we should switch to English
yes that's a good idea Professor uh doct
uh how we should doctor Professor
Lawrence will do Lawrence will do hello
hello Lawrence thank you very much for
coming to our podcast it's a big
privilege it's a pleasure to be here how
do we found Slovakia so far is it your
first time here or it's my first time in
Slovakia yeah it's been I've had a
lovely Whirlwind time here so far and uh
enjoyed the Old Town last night walking
around okay met some fun statues yeah we
have a lot of fun statues but no worries
usually it isn't disc cold the beginning
of September it's it's okay I I live in
Canada
so so this is baby cold should we blame
the climate change for this weather or
no there's a difference between weather
and climate and people confuse them all
the time so weather happens on a day
climate happens in everywhere over time
but still like uh well climate stist are
telling extreme weather is more probable
so maybe yeah yeah but it's you're right
probability is is different so you can
say the probability is greater and in
fact something although I talked about
climate here yesterday something that is
interesting that I talk about in the
book that I didn't talk about is the
fact that there's an if you actually
look at the weather everywhere on Earth
on a given day
and then you can actually begin to see a
signal for for climate change and you
know on a given Place obviously the
variation is such uh that you can't
really tell but if you if you look at
all the places and look at the average
deviation from the average temperature
um there you can actually see some
statistically significant changes so
even weather gives a signal for climate
change
mhm okay you wrote book about climate
change uh 4 years ago probably during Co
yeah because we started our podcast
during the time and you have some
references to covid and lockdowns and so
so on uh how was it to write book about
climate change during um biggest
pandemic of Our Lives it was uh well it
the the pandemic of course was awful but
it was a blessing if you're writing a
book I couldn't do anything else and and
I I think I was telling uh Samuel that
uh most of my books have taken on
average two years to write that book
took 10 weeks to write because I had
absolutely nothing else to do and and
everything else I was doing was canceled
and and you know to tell you the
truth I was thinking about what people
were doing on the front lines and trying
to help people and I I thought what can
I do and I thought well I maybe this
would be a useful thing to do so that
actually motivated me to write the book
then oh okay great and you uh started
your book saying that why astrophysicist
and uh would run book about climate
change can you walk us through this
process because I found it very
fascinating your thought process well
yeah because there are two there's a lot
number of reasons why I wrote the book
first of all um
well
primarily I wrote a book I wanted to
write a book about just the signs of
climate change because at least in the
United States but I think elsewhere
there many people who want to deny the
existence of climate change primarily
because they they're worried that people
are going to tell them what to do
they're going to take away their cars or
or not you know something like that and
so they don't want to hear it and when
you don't want to hear it you tend to
stop listening to anything and you would
and you're willing to not believe the
data so if I could just write a book
about the science and not tell people
what to do that maybe I might reach more
people who could at least understand the
the science behind it realize it was
real and fundamental and and well
established and then they could decide
you know you could look at it and decide
it's it's not worth doing anything if
that's what you that's what you think um
and so that was part of it but but
also as a non-climate
scientist the impression that I get from
many people is they think that climate
science is first speculative and
secondly based on detailed computer
models than we can that we can't trust
and um I think that's obviously mistake
and I suspect many of the climate
scientists sort of sometimes can't tell
as we say in English the forest for the
trees namely get so stuck in details
that you don't step back and and I
thought it would be if if if I as a
first a scientist and secondly as
someone who spends a lot of time
explaining things to the public if I
couldn't explain it in a way that was
clear then how could I expect anyone to
understand it so I thought I thought
it's perfectly reasonable for a uh a a
reasonably educated non-climate
scientists to try and talk about it and
then
what became more fun is that I thought
the science is fascinating and the
history is fascinating and the more I
delt into it the more I found it uh
really kind of interesting to see the
the various episodes that that impacted
on our present understanding yeah the
history was very interesting because one
of the first people I don't remember the
name of the scientist that proposed the
climate change was from Norway and he
was excited about the climate change and
the warming of the climate yeah Sweden
Sweden actually Sweden Sor yeah no
that's right he was really hoping that
he he he saw this as a great
opportunity for Scandinavia to get
better yeah he was very optimistic he
was an interesting guy Arena he was the
first there again I'll give you a little
snippet because there were fascinating
Parts about his life he was the first uh
Swedish uh Nobel Prize winner in
chemistry which is interesting since he
was the head of the
Nobel but it turns out he did important
things but he but he throughout his life
he he somehow managed eek out um success
out of failure he got a he got the one
of the lowest grades for his PhD exam
and he he convinced him to raise the
grade then he got a position even though
most of the people didn't want to give
him a professorship and then he became
head of the University even though
people didn't like him and then he head
of the Nobel Institute but he did
important work so so he was social P
um but his work was influential yeah but
he wasn't really because somehow he
overcame all of that and and and got
these every good position and uh uh and
and interestingly enough uh he he he
used the work in in his thinking of
climate change was strongly based on an
earlier scientist hogman who was a
geoscientist who did the kind of
calculations I really like he and I I
talked about it here the other day and
it's in the book that he um hogr asked
an amazing question often when you talk
to people about climate change they
think well how can humans affect the
climate I mean we're just this puny
beings here and and he he asked well he
could estimate how much carbon there was
in the atmosphere because even then
there was a rough idea knowing how much
it was and you add it all up it's about
600 gigatons 600 billion tons and um and
then he said what happened how how thick
a layer would that be if you liquefied
it or or turned into a solid and it's
only a millimeter thick and he said well
let's look at the soil on Earth life
already affects things much more than a
millimeter so probably life could affect
the amount of carbon in the atmosphere
was a really brilliant kind of backof
the envelope calculation which I think
is so important in physics and this is
very misleading about the atmosphere
like it seems It's stretching all the
way up if you liquid ey it would be 10 m
that's the pressure of it so yeah and
you know and and the other thing um
actually it was a um it was a a a friend
of mine actually a well-known scientist
Martin Ree who who was we were talking
and and people say well how can how can
such a small amount of carbon affect you
know the our the heat that coming from
the the Sun and everything else well it
if you think about it if you take a
little piece of paper and put over your
head it it blocks the Sun out pretty
well and it's pretty and it's pretty
thin compared to the weight of the
entire atmosphere but somehow it can it
can have a dramatic effects so it's not
too surprising that small things can
Happ and if there is a Mist yeah you can
see nothing B ex like today sort of in a
way so you said that well you are
cosmologist but you can write about
simple stuff about climate but I think
there is more to it because yesterday
two quantum gravity guys met at the
stage discussing this so I think it's
not like you can write about climate but
your carer made you like sensitive to
important details and you can explain
them simply so it's you know when you
can you you want to write and make
podcast about Universe you have to be
good at picking the stuff that can be
explained and that can put together some
kind of narrative about the complex
topic so I think it's you are
underselling yourself it's not just
about like you can write about the
simple stuff but they good at picking
the important points and well the more
you do it I think the more experience
you have learning what works and what
doesn't work but thank you yeah I I um
yeah obviously I spend a fair amount of
time on it and uh
and you know I don't I don't know if
you've had this experience I've written
a dozen books and and uh and I often
forget what I put in them and um and
sometimes I have to admit I read it and
go hey that's not too bad these guys
smart yeah so uh you said that uh you
try to not to touch some sensitive
points because people get very like
polarized and this topic same as during
the pandemic the topic got very
polarizing as well but do you think is
this like a sign of stubbornness or we
are we have failing education so people
are not capable of grasping those
complex topics or I think it's all of
that I think people are stubborn people
want to believe first of all everyone
wants to believe what they want to
believe that's so we have to understand
that and scientists are the same way and
the whole the whole point is that
science overcomes the stubbornness of
scientists when they're wrong the
scientific process overcomes the natural
tendency of scientists to want to
believe things that are that they like
rather than the way they really are but
I think we also uh are are uh are doing
a disservice in the way we educate
people about things and and it's not um
I think it's important to realize that I
I avoided subjects that I didn't think
were relevant to understand the science
but I don't believe one should steer
away from sens topics if they're
relevant and I think that's that's uh
really important but you know we we
don't expect people when it comes to
Scientific issues we don't expect people
to think and that's really surprising me
because you know if you have a history
book or an economics book or a social
science book you expect people to work
through complicated arguments in order
but when it comes to science we we give
up expecting people to even see an
equation and some somehow be able to
understand what it means and people are
actually capable of doing it but they
convince themselves they not and I think
um we do people a disservice by by
catering to that willingness to to not
uh have any quantitative thinking about
things and and you see it a lot in in in
simple things uh if you just estimate
things you can guess whether you're
right or wrong and you know i' SE I
remember maybe this has happened to you
but you go to the grocery store and
there's a Casher they're doing and they
make a stake you know and you have three
items and they go oh it's
$3,000 you know hold on a second but
that's what the machine says 2000 yeah
yeah and and you know and you say that
you know they say that's what the
machine says so so it's really useful to
have these tools and um you know I wrote
a book called in fear of physics uh once
and it was about the tools that we used
to try and understand the world because
cuz science is all about taking a very
complicated world and in some sense
simplifying it enough so we can extract
out the important details be because you
know just understanding any given thing
how a piece of paper Falls is so
complicated that if you didn't as
Galileo did get you know avoid the idea
of of air and and and and all of that
you you wouldn't be able to extract out
the important principles that ultimately
reveal the way the universe works and
regarding the difficulties when you are
I don't know writing about Universe I
think there is a natural letter MH you
are increasingly
discovering more difficult stuff with
climate it's like simple equations and
then very quickly it's like super
computer simulation yesterday during
your presentation it was very quickly
from uh Stefan boltzman law to super
computer simulations about so how to
bridge this Gap INX I it's fing you
think it was very quickly I supect if
you ask the audience they wouldn't think
that because the simple stuff was
complicated for them that was you know
when I put a what a simple equation I
could just see the horror on people's
faces when I is talking um and and again
but the essential idea I showed sort of
heris the effect of of of carbon changes
how how it changes the absorption of the
atmosphere and and then I indeed I
showed a super computer calculation that
that mimicked it but and I think the the
the important thing is to say that it's
not as if the supercomputer calculations
demonstrate anything any new fundamental
physical processes they just allow us to
understand the details and climate and
the details of climate are complicated
the overall picture of the effect on the
earth and its overall change in
temperature is not is not particularly
complicated but you know there's lots of
effects there's there's currents there's
winds there's all sorts of things
there's clouds there's all sorts of
things that when you add the details one
by one make it much more complicated but
that's true of life in general and the
idea is often the important thing is to
is to know what to throw out and what
not to throw out and that that's almost
an art in science but generally you know
I think I started my book fear of
physics with a famous joke at least
among the physics Community which uh um
and I'm sure you've heard it in
different context but uh the joke goes
that the that a u a psychologist an
engineer and a physicist were called
into a dairy farm to um to because the
farm wanted to produce more and and they
each were given a week to explore and
analyze the things and the psychologist
comes back and says well you should
paint the barn green because the cows
will be happier and they'll give more
milk and the engineer says well I've
checked the size of the milking tubes
and they're and they're a little too
small they should be bigger so you could
the milk can flow more carefully and the
physicist comes out and first asks for a
Blackboard of course and gets a
Blackboard and then draws a a circle and
says assume the cow is a
sphere anyway yeah sphere in a vacuum
yeah and uh maybe one last thing about
the climate change yesterday you
mentioned GE engineering and we got many
well many people ask us to make an
episode about this so what is your St on
this well My Views have changeed
somewhat
um by the way I think it's inevitable I
think it'll happen whether we like it or
not because I think you mean on here on
Earth or here on Earth yeah yeah I don't
think it's going to happen on Mars no
matter what well not in the firstable
Future No Matter What Elon Musk might
want to do and I don't even think he'll
get to Mars but that's a different um
but uh the point is that I suspect that
that political systems will hamper the
response to climate change and there may
be some climate emergencies andc as I
pointed out yesterday G engineering has
the virtue and also the danger that
unlike trying to reduce carbon output
which requires cooperation of all the
countries in the world basically
if you want to put aerosols in the in
the atmosphere any one country any one
business for that matter could do it and
and and and that means that you don't
need have the whole world agree to
something but it also means so that's
the danger any one country could decide
to do it uh but also it's the virtue
because it means it can be done I used
to be opposed to to geoengineering
because we don't know what's going to
happen when you put aerosols in we know
yes you block some sunlight but what
other things will happen and one of the
things that I did mention would happen
that I hadn't realized I I learned from
uh Elizabeth Colbert's uh who she's a
she's a great science writer uh her book
under a white sky is that that with if
you put tend to put aerosols in the
atmosphere the sky color will change
from Blue to White and so children in
the future might won't be looking at a
blue sky they'll be looking at a white
Sky which seems kind of sad and and
unromantic but I'm not as opposed to
geoengineering as I was because again
one of my GEOS science colleagues
pointed out to me that unlike carbon
which more or less stays in the
atmosphere for almost a thousand years
aerosols put in the atmosphere dissipate
within a year or so so even if there are
negative features they won't last a th
turn it off quickly you can turn it off
relatively quickly and so it's the kind
of experiment that doesn't seem
horrendous so I'm not as opposed to the
idea of geng engineering as I was before
and and you can also do experiments and
some people are doing experiments simple
experiments with aols to see what the
impact is and um the other negative that
people point out and it is somewhat true
is it's not a cure it's a it's a it's a
Band-Aid and and so it allows you to
take more time to do what really needs
to be done and some people say well if
you have your geoengineering then you
don't even then there'll be no
motivation to try
and exactly my point what would be the
motivation for the countries to well
yeah because because you know you can't
keep adding and I mean I think well one
can never underestimate the stupidity of
government so all overestimated so yeah
anyway okay so maybe we should move to
different topic sure that's fine yeah so
to cosmology okay I kind of figured we
were going to head there yeah yeah I
brought two
books so uh yesterday uh I mentioned uh
the vacuum dispersion effect yeah you
seem you seem skeptical about vacuum
dispersion being observable so can you
just elaborate a little well I mean it
is an interesting idea that at very
small scales which can only be probed by
very high energies that the nature of
SpaceTime might be slightly different in
quantum gravity and the highest energy
cosmic rays are approaching the kind of
energies where that might be observable
MH um I just haven't seen any convincing
arguments it it's more hopeful than than
than than suggestive I guess point is
yeah look for it um but but I guess in
my having been around for a long time
I'm I'm a skeptical and generally most
ideas are wrong that is completely true
in
science at least yeah if they weren't
anyone could do it right and so this is
very hopeful and most hopeful things are
are just that so I guess that's my kind
of uh skepticism more I haven't seen any
if I saw that there was a convincing
first principles argument that this is
an effect that must be observable then
I'd be less uh less skeptical it's the
same thing about something that I spent
a lot of time on which is gravitational
waves from the from the early Universe
from something called
inflation uh it'd be profoundly
important to observe them and I spent a
lot of time arguing where you might
observe them and and and what their
effects might be and in fact my my
colleague Frank W and I
showed I think remark remarkably that if
you could measure gravitational waste or
inflation you could prove that gravity
is a quantum theory empirically mhm it's
a it's a really neat very simple
argument can you repeat the simpler
argument for this yeah yeah but but let
me before I repeat the argument um but
at the same time there's no compelling
argument that they should be visible
that that Ian the scale where
gravitational waves would be actually
observable is a very is a very specific
scale associated with this period in the
early Universe called inflation and if
it changed by a factor of two or four
they'd be unobservable so while it would
be very important I'm not it's it's we'd
have to be very lucky if it if if
they're observable and for a while it
looked like we were lucky we there was
small period when they thought they
observed them for there was a paper that
came out and it looked like it was an
effect and it was very important anyway
the the reason that you can show uh this
in a way that I could explain is that
well what we used was something called
demential analysis actually in the end I
we did a detailed calculation but
dimensional and physicists use
dimensional analysis because in the
universe there are certain quantities
that describe how the universe works and
they have Dimensions like space and and
time and mass basically they're the
major dimensions and almost every
physical quantity can be described in
terms of how space time and mass okay
okay and when we looked at the at at the
at the production of gravitational waves
we looked for its dependence on a key
quantity called the planks constant
which is which tells you that you know
if the planks constant went to zero
quantum mechanical effects would go to
zero the fact that it's nonzero
represents the fact that quantum
mechanics exists and changes the
predictions of universe compared to
Classic mechanics and we showed just by
dimensional analysis that the that that
if you want to calculate the the the the
density of gravitational waves from
inflation that in fact the only
combination even without knowing how to
do it the only combination of space time
and mass and plank Conant would be such
that it would depend as a on a PO
positive power of Plank's constant and
therefore if if you measured it it would
show that that it was quantum mechanical
because if Plank's constant went to zero
then then turned off so it was really
kind of simple to show that it was
inherently a quantum mechanical process
which the the equations the calculations
are done using quantum mechanics but
that doesn't prove its quantum
mechanical namely I could calculate how
a baseball thrown from my hand gets to a
pitcher I could calculate it using
quantum mechanical wave function was all
that but in the end I'd end up with
Newton's Laws I'd end up with classical
result so the fact that I can use
quantum mechanics to calculate something
it's not surprising because after all
quantum mechanics describes the universe
but but uh certain results are classical
and don't need quantum mechanics to do
them and in fact would would be exactly
the same even if the world wasn't
quantum mechanical like a pitcher
throwing a baseball but in this case we
showed it wouldn't it wouldn't it would
vanish and so it would be really
remarkable are you hopeful for the Lisa
observatory in this regard because it
should be sensitive exactly to this part
of spectrum yeah but I think I think
yeah I think there of course I'm hopeful
I love anytime we open a new window on
the universe would tend to be surprised
Lisa probably actually Lisa itself
probably won't be sensitive enough you'd
need a super Lisa already leis is
probably still a few orders of magnitude
away from that there are other ways to
do it by looking at something called The
Cosmic microwave background radiation
and it's what and its properties which
is how people thought they discovered it
in the first place something called the
polarization of that and that those sens
those experiments are getting more
sensitive and um and you know but
they're the ones that
in order to see it has to be very
special value otherwise I think we have
to wait not for Lisa but super Lisa or
maybe super super Lisa and um and that's
going to be quite a while yeah but if
Lisa sees nothing will there be well
motivation to build super Lisa or it
will
see super massive black mergers and yeah
yeah it'll see something that's the
point it's going to see something and
it's not like say particle accelerators
where where the LOD and
collider discovered the higs particle
but it hasn't discovered anything else
and and and as I've told physicists even
before I said the worst possible thing
could happen is the discovery of the
higs and nothing else because then we we
we know there are problems and Mysteries
in the standard model of particle
physics but I don't think we can go up
to politicians and say guess what we
haven't seen anything give us more money
yeah and so that's they're trying to do
that yeah but it's hard it's hard and uh
I mean seeing nothing is sometimes very
important in science it really tells you
that something and there's some famous
experiments the Michaels and moley
experiment the fact that you couldn't
see evidence that the Earth was moving
through some background ether was a
demonstration of Einstein Ser relativity
working uh so so null experiments as
they're called in physics can be very
important but but um uh I remember
actually talking to a young faculty
member when I was chairman of Department
who was applying for a job and they had
been looking for a certain kind of dark
matter and hadn't seen anything and
ruled out a whole range but but for
any physicists who weren't in that field
having someone having an experimental
result that doesn't give any any any
positive thing was not a was not a good
uh was not didn't make him optimistic
that he'd get tenure that way yeah you
wrote book about Universe coming uh to
existence from nothing it was like 12
years ago uh really that far sorry I
didn't want yeah all right time flies
yeah time feels like yesterday yeah yeah
does has your claim aged well uh during
those 12 years I think so I think it
it's aged beautifully cuz it was
correct no I don't think there's
anything um that's changed uh in in any
deep way uh uh about the arguments I
made and because can you summarize those
yeah and and and I mean if anything I
was hoping for you know more
experimental data on certain things but
that that hasn't happened but but it but
it was a plausibility argument which
which really ultimately needs a real
theory of quantum gravity to to be
proved but the argument is really quite
simple first of all if gravity is a
quantum theory the variables of gravity
are space and time einen showed us that
space time is the curvature of space
time reflects the gravitational field
and vice versa so gravity is described
as by the properties of space and time
and if gravity is a quantum theory then
those variables are become Quantum
variables space and time are quantum
mechanical in fact as as we were talking
about earlier some people hope that fact
would allow you to see what you said was
a dispersion in very high energy uh
cosmic rays um but in any case so space
and time are the fundamental variables
of gravity if they're quantum mechanical
then they behave Quantum mechanically
that means they fluctuate and space
times can pop into existence and out of
existence just like particles Elementary
particles pop in and out of existence
all the time we know that these things
called virtual particles even though you
can't measure them
directly we can measure their effects on
the properties of atoms and they and
they allow us to calculate quantities to
13 decimal places we get the right
answer we we'd get the wrong answer if
you didn't include the effects of these
so-called virtual particles that are
popping in and out of existence so if
space time is quantum mechanical then
space times can pop in the whole
universes can pop into existence out of
nothing literally namely no space no
time now we know that virtual particles
are virtual because two particles pop
into existence a particle and AN empti
particle they violate energy
conservation if they have mass right
because first you have nothing there and
suddenly you have particles with mass
the well the but the the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle quantum mechanics
is is gives you a little loophole it
says you can't measure things exactly
you if you have only a certain amount of
time you can only measure energy with a
certain accuracy MH and so if these
particles that kind of slip in there if
they exist for a Time shorter then you
can measure that violation in energy
conservation that would be due to their
existence if then they're allowed it's
as I like to say it's like politics and
and and and uh and business if if no one
can measure it then anything goes and
and it's that way with it's it's that
way with with with with Elementary
particles so they can exist for a very
short time but particles that that that
say carry no energy could pop into into
existence and they could exist for
arbitrarily long times and that happens
in nature okay so if you had a universe
that say had zero total energy it could
pop into existence and not have to
disappear and and there are strong
suggestions that our universe has zero
total energy first of all but most
universes will that virtual universes if
you want will disappear in a very short
time you could ask what would the
properties of a universe be that would
pop into existence by the laws of
quantum mechanics and last you know 13.8
billion years okay without disappearing
and it turns out if you look at it it
would have exactly the properties of the
universe that we see today essentially
now that's highly suggestive but it's
not proof it just says well you know it
it it a universe that did do just that
could look like our universe and and if
we see our universe looking like that
it's suggestive that that happened and
it shows you that without any
Supernatural Shenanigans you can create
a universe or no not create that's not
the good word a universe can
spontaneously a r careful about yeah
yeah exactly yeah yeah but exactly uh
because English fails your language
fails you all the time but uh so a
universe can come into existence from
nothing and by that and and I talk about
the nature of nothing a lot in the book
and people get hung up especially
philosophers and theologians get hung up
a lot on this idea of nothing but what I
mean for the most part here is no space
No Time namely everything we see no
space no time no particles everything
that exists in our universe now did not
exist now whether anything else exists
is a different question but our universe
didn't exist and then it suddenly
existed and so something different could
exist but not the space and time that we
know from our yeah yeah and that's the
and you know and and and the other
question is May it may be an interesting
question for some people it's not an
interesting question for me well in
principle it's an interesting question
but the but the really remarkable thing
the thing we should be amazed about is
that our whole universe containing 100
billion galaxies each containing 100
billion stars all of that could come
from nothing it seems to require
something to you know some Creator and
the fact that it doesn't it's it seems
to me it's worth celebrating and that's
so I think one of the reasons why my
friend Richard Dawkins argued and I you
know in that at least in some sense and
and I and and one shouldn't put too much
emphasis on this that that it it
proceeds to take what what Darwin did
for for biology to The Next Step Darwin
showed that the complexity of Life Could
arise simply by Evolution and didn't
require divine intervention and a
universe of nothing shows in principle
how the complexity of our universe could
arise from nothing without divine
intervention and so he he put it on a a
similar framework I but you know it's
not to suggest that a universe of
nothing is the same as as the origin of
the which which was a profoundly
important book yeah so in string theory
or maybe in M Theory the picture is like
you have a 10 dimensional something and
then three dimension start just
expanding is this the same picture like
we had not nothing before but we were
part of something different and then
spontaneously there was some face if I
don't think well yes and no because I
think in string the I'm theing it's it's
the the it's so vague as as to say Yeah
well yeah it looks the same but no
there's not mechanisms for which that
happens in fact I'd have to say that one
of the biggest failings of strength
Theory and I think Richard fan felt this
way even when he was still alive in the
80s is that it requires in general
Universe with more than four dimensions
but it doesn't in any way explain why
the universe we live is four-dimensional
he said that was one of its biggest
failings in fact he he he he argued that
it makes excuses rather than predictions
and and so uh yeah think theory in
principle allows although it even now we
understand the whole nature of
Dimensions itself is it is kind of a a
vague concept but but it requires
generally more than four dimensions and
we we don't observe them I've never
walked into an extra Dimension that I
know of well me are just too large yeah
yeah and but in any case uh but but it
doesn't explain why the four dimensions
that we see are large uh and why other
dimensions are small there's no natural
mechanism that in the theory that
suggests that and it could just be an
accident and that's generally
unfortunately the argument that's now G
given well it's an accident if it was
any difference we wouldn't be having
this podcast right now and and that's
potentially true but it's not an
explanation well maybe the universe
doesn't owe us a good explanation no it
doesn't and and it well I mean it's not
a it's not compelling m and it may but
it may be true and the universe is the
way it is whether we like it or not and
and that anthropic kind of argument
which we use a lot including
understanding the energy of nothing
which is one of the reasons I wrote that
book because nothing can have energy uh
it may be philosop to be philosophers
have to be really mad at you well I
don't know they get mad at me for a lot
of
things but uh uh you know that it just
may be true that universe is an accident
and the pro fundamental properties of
universe are accidental it's
disappointing for someone like me who's
old enough to have wanted to become a
scientist of want by wanting to explain
why the universe had to be the way it is
and that's the way science used to work
and and and in the end if we sh say well
the fundamental reason is you know
argument is that it doesn't have to be
the way it is it's just an accident uh
that may be true so we'll see and maybe
we'll just find an argument for why
three is the right number there's a
newpaper on archive every couple of
months yeah and they're all wrong but uh
but you know but uh yeah maybe well one
hopes that it would be nice if you did
if this really was a fundamental theory
that was right if it if it answered at
least some fundamental questions about
the universe but right now I have to say
a wild string theory has led to
remarkably interesting mathematics and
insights into certain physical
theories um that have been really useful
it hasn't in my opinion
fundamentally explained anything about
the universe that we
see uh some people would say it's given
some arguments about the nature of black
holes and and what's called the entropy
of black holes sort of but it still
hasn't answered the fundamental
questions about the ultimate behavior of
black Hool so I think it's Fallen far
short of what we hoped it would do that
doesn't mean it's wrong and that doesn't
mean it's not worth pursuing but but it
hasn't explained the key things such as
why we live in a universe of three space
dimensions why the energy of empty space
isn't zero but it's very small and
positive uh because in general if you
asked a thing theorist if you locked
them in a room and didn't give them any
data most of them don't care about data
anyway but uh if you if you didn't care
give any data they'd say oh well the
energy of empty space is negative and
and it isn't so uh you know it's not got
a good batting average in that regard
you know my friend again my friend Frank
WI has a good analogy that I like he
says String Theory um what string the
like to do is they like to throw darts
on a wall and then after darts are there
they draw bulls eyes around
them so maybe just to finish this topic
you mentioned a person connecting black
holes to string theory recently on your
Origins podcast you had lonar saskin yes
yeah and his
description of our universe is
completely different to what we are used
to his famous the universe as a hologram
yeah do you think we are due to
completely different perspective are we
waiting for next Einstein to completely
reorganize physics well I I think that
quantum gravity will probably require
some great leaps and it's going to be a
lot take a long time to do if ever
because it's also hard to remember
Einstein was Guided by observations no
matter what people think he was
ultimately Guided by observations to to
lead to his and confirm his General
general theory of relativity but but the
but the notion of the world as a
hologram of course
does the mathematics behind that does
come from String Theory at some level
and uh one M Thea's arguments about
something called duality of but um and
and so I suspect that that the ultimate
description of nature will be more
strange than anything we can imagine
because the universe is stranger so far
the imagination of the universe exceeds
the imaginative human beings so and and
it would be amazing by the way even
though it's extremely well motivated and
I know Lenny strongly thinks that string
theory is is is probably
correct uh and has argum and has worked
on for a long time and and there are
it's really well motivated by what we
understand but I still kind of think it
would be amazing if it were actually
true because most physical ideas are
wrong but I felt that way to be fair
about the higs mechanism about the higs
particle I thought for sure the higs
particle didn't exist cuz it just seemed
too simple a way to solve the problem so
the standard model and I you like The
Simple Solutions well you know it just
was It was kind of slimy it was just
sort of okay put it all create a new
particle and it solves all these
problems and I thought well probably
reality is much more complicated but it
looks like that at some level and I was
very surprised that the higs existed so
um so you know it could be that this
this this stab in the dark well
motivated stab in the dark is right but
we just have to realize that most stabs
in the dark in physics don't work so we
shall see about and that's great you
know that's what's wonderful not knowing
as I said in my most recent book uh
which is called the known unknowns uh at
least in England and since you get the
English books here uh rather than the
American ones um and uh um and it's
about what we know we don't know about
the universe which is really fascinating
to and and and not knowing is is really
at the heart of science because it's an
invitation to discover so I wish more
people would be more more parents and
more teachers and more politicians would
be willing to say I don't know because
that's that's exciting that's not
embarrassing that's exciting because it
means there's something to learn and so
we'll see is a wonderful thing it's an
invitation to young people to say
there's there's there's a lot left to
learn and I remember when I was a young
person it was a book by Richard Fineman
that motivated me was called the
character of physical law that made me
realize that it wasn't all understood
that there was a lot left to learn and I
think that we have to you know that's
the kind of thing can excite young
people to realize that there is there is
sort of job security in science because
there's a lot we don't and I expect it
it's not going to end I don't there's
all even if even if we had a so-called
as I used to say Theory of Everything
which is not really a theory of
everything it's a theory of very little
string theory is really a theory that
would if we had it a theory of quantum
gravity it would help us understand the
origins of the big bang and the ultimate
fade of black holes but other than that
wouldn't be particularly it wouldn't enh
enhance our understanding of anything
else in the world it just gives some
fundamental descriptions but there's
still a lot of things that need to be
understood that how oatmeal boils how
you know Quantum properties of matter
and and so there there's a there's lots
there's there's a lot left to learn
about the universe and it's and it's not
as if it's going to that that process is
going to end soon you are very active in
your science Outreach programs uh
throughout the podcast or throughout
your books uh uh last book about climate
change you wrote in 10 weeks but there
are people that make 10 seconds or 30
seconds videos on Tik Tok or other
social platforms and their Outreach is
no offense to you but bigger much bigger
than yours uh is it frustrating or do
you see uh scientists reaching to the
Layman throughout the social platforms
well I think you know it depends on your
on the day doesn't it um look I don't
think one can be I mean one can choose
to be frustrated by the fact that
certain things are popular but it's
always been that way there's nothing new
about that that that that certain things
are always popular you know and and it's
fun to ha popular things yeah so that's
all right but I think you can use it and
I've tried to do that I've tried to use
the popular culture as a way to get
people interested in science my book the
physics of Star Trek for example was
hugely popular prob because I used Star
Trek which was a cultural phenomenon in
science fiction and people could
appreciate that who who didn't
appreciate science so I think rather
than being frustrated we should try and
use what the what the public is
interested in as a as a hook to help
them get interested in the real universe
and that's partly what I've tried to do
in everything I've done including the
podcast which is to connect science and
culture it's not just scientists I
talked to it's writers and actors and
directors and journalists and and and
you know artists and musicians as well
as scientists because it's all part of a
whole the The Wonder of human culture
and and the and the ideas that are
driving our sense of self in the 21st
century but it's also like okay social
networks are giving new tools to sand
communicators but it's also forming the
expectations of the audience and
shortening the attention span so yeah it
is for writing books yeah no no it's
true people if it's longer than a tweet
a lot of kids don't want to read it yeah
exactly and yeah and that's a yeah
that's a that's a problem um and and and
it's it's a it's interesting because
when I I've been writing books for a
long time and I think I wrote my first
book maybe 30 over 30 years ago and was
fascinating to see how I've had a few
very big selling books okay and it and
say the physics of Star Trek which I
think came out in '95 or something I
forget something like that 93 94 95 and
then the universe nothing both of which
were big New York Times bestsellers
let's say but the number of books that
it takes to become a New York bestseller
has dropped by a factor of two in that
inum because people don't buy books
anymore people don't read them and um
and we can bemoan that fact but things
change and so uh we it's a challenge to
us to find new ways to reach people I
think it's sad of course as someone who
likes reading that young people don't
like to read as much but you know the
world changes and and you can spend all
your time complaining about it or you
can move along with it or you can try
and find ways to be interesting enough
or attractive enough to cry and get
people to to pick up a book and um I
guess I'd rather try that than just give
up Malcolm Gladwell recommends that
dropping small rewards as a writer every
couple of pages some piece of trivia
that people can just well shove off to
their friends so do you think about this
when you're are writing like you are
writing to a different readers as 20
years ago well
yes to some
extent I but I've I guess I've been
Guided by the same principles when
writing as well as lecturing which is to
try and recognize that people have a
limited attention span in listening or
reading and so that Concepts need to
can't be too long and also you need to
give people a break in between them with
something relaxing and also when I write
I try and make it not consequential so
that if there's something you don't
understand it doesn't affect the whole
rest of the book which allows me because
I do believe strongly in not dumbing
down everything I think people do want
to be challenged sometimes at least
there's certain readers that do and in
every one of my books I try and throw
things in to challenge certain readers
but at the same time
hopefully those readers who really find
that part difficult can skip it and and
not and not lose track of the rest of
the book so it's a combination of things
yeah when I started writing I hated like
personal stories because like everything
you read about gravity has to mention
Einstein somehow and I just I thought
this is cheating but there a static
writing books I realized well this is a
good you know to cool down the pace and
just you know write one page about life
of Newton or something like that and
well people like personal things yeah
and and I also I'm fascinated by history
anyway and I often find it useful and
it's also fun for me the point is that
people don't realize that everything I
do is for me ultimately I but I don't
think that makes me special so I write
books for obviously with a reason but I
write books for myself in some sense and
so for me a book is a voyage of
Discovery if it's just a regurgitation
that's not interesting and so I learn
things in every book I write I I pick a
subject sometimes which I may you know I
have some basic ideas about but which
are going to require a lot of learning
and that's that's why if you don't do
that you tend to write the same book
over and over again and I know a number
of people who do that and I won't
mention names but yeah yeah but uh
uh giving myself that challenge means
that the books are different but it also
means that it's interesting for me and
part of it is history The Learning the
history is fascinating like in the
climate change I didn't know about the
history and it's some of it's just
fascinating yeah and yeah and when you
start write when you write your first
sentence what percentage of the book is
already in your head and uh what is to
be discovered it's a good question first
of all the books usually take me in
direct directions I didn't expect mhm I
used to say it takes me about half the
time of if I look at the full time of
writing a book the first chapter is half
the time MH and the rest of the book is
the other half first chapter is because
because I've got to find and I try a lot
of different things and I don't know
where I'm going and by the time I finish
the first chapter I have a sense of
where it's going and then but then
sometimes it takes me in directions I
never expected and so uh and and and as
when I do an audio book when you write
when you record an audiobook I often
redo the first chapter at the end
because your pace of your talking
changes in the way and the first chapter
may sound different than the rest of the
book but the same thing happens with my
book sometimes I'll go back and after
and reflect on what's what's actually
there and and and make some changes at
the beginning mhm do you rewrite a lot
because I hate it yeah I know I know
well everyone hates it everyone hates it
uh I I I try to do it at a minimum MH
um there have been only a few occasions
where I've had to drastically rewrite a
book my book on Fineman which is one of
my favorite books uh a book called
Quantum man which is a scientific
biography of Richard Fineman the first
real popular scientific biography there
were books about his life and all of
that but I wanted to talk about why sure
he was an interesting character but
that's not a reason to understand I
wanted to talk about why he mattered as
a scientist and and I was asked to write
that book uh and I've never wrote a
proposal and I I was just honored to do
it cuz mostly cuz I thought this will
force me to read all of his papers which
otherwise I wouldn't have the discipline
to do
MH and I when I wrote that book I I I
wrote it and the the publisher who asked
me to write it when I sent him a first
draft of the first half of it by the way
I usually don't do with Publishers but I
did in this case um came back and said
what what's all this
science and uh and then I realized I
didn't have I rewrote it but I have to
rewrite it significantly in a sense
because I I what I did was I worked his
life biography into it in a way that
would all the science was still there
but it wasn't as it wasn't obviously as
noticeable because I sent it back to him
with this you know weaving these
personal stories in the mid and they
said oh great this is what we wanted but
all the stuff that was originally there
was there that was probably the most
drastic version of of of rewriting but
no I don't rewrite a lot I I uh By the
time I get to the writing stage I I kind
of know where I'm heading MH yeah so
maybe to move to a different form of art
there is a movie you told me about
yesterday the unbelievers oh yeah that
describes you and Richard Dawkins is
sort of a rock stars touring with
scientific content and this year I was
at six different festivals with science
talks and discussion so on but I noticed
there is difference between how music
makes people feel and how even a good
talk make people feel so is there a huge
difference are we tickling different
part of the audience brains or well it
depends what you how you're talking I
think the AHA experience is orgasmic I
think museums I used to work in a
science museum when I was a kid which by
the way impacted on obviously on the way
I try and explain things it was it was a
very useful learning experience and
unbelievably useful learning experience
but the museums talk about this AA
experiments everyone has it when there's
something that they underst understand
something basic that they understand for
the first time that they never really
realize they understand that aha
experience is seductive and impure and
pleasurable and I don't think it's that
different than than great art or music
the the the feeling that you get from it
um I the difference
is that I think music more than art but
music let let's talk about that in
particular reaches people more easily
mhm we have an
innate evolutionary appreciation for
music even if we can't do it and and you
don't have to know anything about music
to either appreciate Bach Kata or Eric
Clapton playing the guitar okay
um and the difference with science is
that there's a higher threshold that you
need to get to before you can appreciate
it so that is definitely true and so
it's easier for music to reach people
more more people more broadly than it is
science and that's just the the way it
is um but I think um uh I think people
can
have the same sense of the Kumbaya
experience you see I mean you know in in
a cal music concert everyone's together
and it's everyone's smiling and there
and lot of people are stoned which is a
different thing but anyway but but uh
but um uh but in but I think you can in
certain in certain events that I've
spoken at in these big big venues that
you get that same sense of community
like-mindedness people there for a
common purpose and enjoying each other I
think one of the people reason people go
to church every Sunday is for that
experience of community so I think we
could you know have quantum mechanics
classes every Sunday and have everyone
together maybe not quantum mechanics
classes but we could we certainly be to
be more serious people have said well
you know religion gives us something
that science doesn't you know and I
think that we can ask what does religion
give us and then ask how can we
reproduce it but with descriptions that
actually describe the world instead of
of fairy tales mhm so it's a different
experience but it can be a deeper one
actually probably because I can
probably quote some pieces of music that
had some impact on my life but maybe
some quotes of Richard dokins is uh we
are all going to die and that makes us
the lucky ones it's deeper than probably
any music well yes you know but that may
but that may be my opic for you to say
that in the sense that I suspect some
people who have an incredible
appreciation for music mhm have that
experience when they hear uh a piece of
music you know Mozart say or a Bach I
mean the the many voices and all of the
rest that I can't get and so they may
have a deep a very deep almost mystical
experience that we don't have and I
think we have an you and as scientists
we we are able to appreciate certain
aspects of science that other people
can't MH we can try and relate it but
you can't reproduce it
um but I think it's also true that that
music in impacts on us in a in a
different cerebral way than than
language and and we
don't again it depends if you're
musically oriented most of us don't
reflect on the music as much as
experience it whereas when it comes to
Scientific discussions or the written
word we reflect on it much more and
therefore it can it can it can have a
deeper or and longer lasting effect an
amazing quote can have a more lasting
effect for most of us although for some
people I suspect a
musical phrase can have a a deep and
Lasting effect you know I wish I wish I
wish I was and often wish I was one of
the people who could get as much I love
music but I'm and but I'm not I play a
number of instruments very badly even
though
as I like to say sometimes and I don't
usually publicly I um I've been
nominated for a Grammy and I I've soled
with the Cleveland Orchestra and I wrote
the the lto for a symphony but I don't
have any musical ability any it doesn't
sound like it I know it sounds good it
sounds good on a piece of paper on paper
it sounds sounds
perfect well Rick Rubin says he says no
he can play no instruments and cannot
produce music on his own but he's just
very good taste and confidence in his
well there you go yeah yeah well I'm I'm
I I I wish I could my daughter was very
Musical and I wish I could sing I wish I
could play instruments I love it and
it's very frustrating in in a way um
that I but but it's nice that I can
appreciate it at least that whereas you
know some people say they can't do math
I think mostly they don't want to spend
the time doing it I realize there's
different abilities but I think most
people can do math without if they if
you know if they work on it we just
don't demand it but um
uh I I think the difference is that I
can appreciate music without having
those abilities and for some for many
people without you can't appreciate the
math without at least a little more work
MH and there is this book good aerb that
yeah one can maybe used to argue that at
the deepest level those completely
different things as art ma mathematics
and so on are someone connected oh sure
yeah that yeah that was a very well good
selling book and I and my my my first
publisher was the same publisher who
published that book and we had long
discussions about it but yeah I mean
there's no doubt they're very M deep
mathematical connections between in some
ways between music and and that but
again experientially the way people
experience mathematics and music is
undeniably different yeah I think yeah
most people would agree with this
statement yeah uh do you think that um
Science Now is a polarization Factor now
in our Society uh well everything is a
polarization Factor now in our society
and it's unfortunate and I think part of
it
is well part of it is just the social
fabric is is is being changed part of it
I think is is an
unfortunate is due to scientists uh I
think with the the co covid pandemic was
for me an opportunity to explain how
science
works one of the things I I having
written about Star Trek that I say that
it's unfortunate about Star Trek is
every time there's a big problem in in
Star Trek they solve it in two hours
they come up with scientific solution
you know takes 45 minutes to figure in
the real world it doesn't it takes years
and decades and decades and when Co hit
I think people had this expectation yeah
we'll be able to understand it and cure
it in a week right and instead it was a
it was an opportunity to say look we
don't understand anything about it
here's how science Works scientists are
going to some scientists are going to
put forward a hypothesis it's going to
be wrong it's going to be tested by
other scientist and we'll slowly learn
more about it and it's actually amazing
that within a year or so we had a
vaccine that that is unbelievable but
instead you had all these people making
the including some science pseudo well
scientists some doctors making these
pronouncements about this is what the
science said when we don't we didn't
know you know because you can't know
because there's no one's it hasn't
existed before there aren't any cases
you don't know how the human body is
going to respond Bond and it would have
been a great chance to say look we don't
know but we're going to try this and it
might not work and we're going to try
this and maybe because we don't know how
it works for safety sake we should try
this but not hey you have to do this
because we know it's going to work and
masks are an example for safety sake
because we don't know let's use masks
and and then here's how vaccines work
and here's how they don't work and
here's how we test them and and it was a
great chance to show at the cutting Edge
how uncertain science really is but some
scientists and other people and
politicians are scared by the word the
notion of uncertainty they have to say
be appear to be certain of the things
and that's really I think did a
disservice because of course when people
are certain about things and they're
wrong people distrust things and and in
the on the whole that that
characteristic of being certain about
things and being wrong is is the generic
property of politicians MH not of
scientists but when scientists have
joined that and and been claimed to be
certain about certain things and been
wrong public confidence in science
decreases so I think it was an a
learning opportunity that that was
unfortunately blown in my opinion mhm
and regarding the polarization
mhm I feel that people are not capable
of maybe disagreeing respectfully
because there are long convers
conversations you probably had with uh
uh Jordan Peterson did as well there was
a strong disagreement but expressed with
respect MH then short clips came from
that on social networks and taken out of
context it seemed like nearly aggressive
so how in this era should we be learning
how to be respectfully disagreeing with
someone but still being you know capable
of reaching well I think one of the few
ways is humor mhm if we if we can laugh
sure and and and make fun of ourselves
that helps MH so I think I think
injecting humor into into human
relations often
diffuses uh otherwise aggressive
aggressiveness but it's hard to it's
hard to I wish I had a Magic Bullet to
solve that problem
because sound bites will always distort
mhm things and and dis agreements don't
sell right if you're try if you're
looking for clickbaits having people say
oh I agree with what you say it's not
going to get a nice
point so that will never be viral yeah
so people are always looking for some
ways to get people to click on something
and and disagreement cells and like sex
and so it's um you just got to
understand that that's the way the world
is and try and and try and um work on
that but but you know I
did as you know I've done I did say
Ricky Jes and I have done a podcast and
and I think um I love him that was an
example of how can use humor to try and
even when you disagree
anyway so yesterday when we spoke and
today during this podcast you mentioned
many interesting people so who can you
recommend someone to pay attention to
like you had your group friend stepen
fry or well there lot look I I yeah I
people there are lots of interesting
people in the world and and uh and so um
yeah pay attention to all the people
that I talked
okay yeah but you know I think uh I I
I'm always for me it's always a pleasure
to discover new people that I didn't
expect and and and and you know and you
know what at some level everyone has
interesting stories to tell or
interesting the comments to have but but
um there are remarkable people um and uh
I think for me as one of the biggest
surprises as as an
academic who sort of revered Academia
for most of my life when I was growing
up and and obviously was involved in it
for many years I used to somehow think
that the most interesting brilliant
people were academics and and it and it
was really a great discovery to find out
that wasn't true MH yeah in what way
like the academics were worse or
non-academics were better um I think
non-academics are you know the point is
that academ is a very safe environment
and even though you know at some level
creative thinking is important you can
survive
very you there's great safety in in in
not varing far from the path if you're
an academic okay um but in other areas
of human activity uh you've got no
safety net and and I'm I'm very
impressed with people who who who could
make achievements in in that environment
so yeah I've discovered and people who
have no classical education and and
they're remark who are remarkable and so
that's great I love I love that is it
like because academics don't have the
skin in the game sometimes yeah I think
it's a combination of that and and there
academics are are often talented in one
thing and and Academia is an environment
where they can where they can utilize
those talents at a very very safe way
with a lot of
support and that's great because it that
that kind of safety net does does allow
incremental progress most academics are
not you know groundbreakers right it's
not that way I mean academ and generally
science proceeds in baby steps the media
make it sound like there's a revolution
every 2 minutes and every there's a new
Einstein every three hours the big leap
and so yeah yeah and it's not and and
although I've always amused when people
say a Quantum Leap because a Quantum
Leap is actually pretty
small but but uh uh anyway um that
environment works but it's it doesn't
encourage necessarily innovators
innovators can survive and and flourish
in that environment too if they want but
it doesn't necessarily encourage that
and and you know I think academics also
it allows people who are timid uh to to
function and most academics generally
and this is part of the problem of
Academia right now and I've been writing
about it it's that that academics don't
want to speak out because most academics
just want to live below the radar they
just want to work on their stuff they
don't want their CH Department chairs or
Deans to find out what they're doing or
ask doing or ask them to do something
else be on a committee or when and so um
speaking out against the kind of threats
to free speech and open inquiry is
something most academics don't want to
do because they get noticed if they do
it and also speaking to the public is
something many academics don't want to
do because it is scary it's it's
suddenly you're open in an environment
that you're not used to and so um you
know Academia has its functions but it's
but it's not uh um it academics are not
necessarily um correct courageous let me
put it that way Lawrence thank you very
much for uh having time to sit with us
and talk with us we are at the end of
our time maybe someday when we will
return to Slovakia we can uh have a
second uh edition of this podcast uh do
you have some parting words for our
listeners to that you want to convey to
them well first of all thank you I
really enjoyed it the quality of the
discussion was really great and I would
love to return thank you again um and I
guess um you know your listeners I just
say don't believe everything you
hear even on this that was implicit but
yeah that was right okay so thank you
very much again have a nice day
[Music]
spacee for